<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Great Basin ecosystem on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>/categories/great-basin-ecosystem/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Great Basin ecosystem on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/great-basin-ecosystem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tail bifurcation in Plestiodon skiltonianus</title>
      <link>/posts/bifurcation_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/bifurcation_paper/</guid>
      <description>As part of our field research, members of the A.P.E. lab occasionally stumble on a novel observation worthy of a published &amp;lsquo;natural history note&amp;rsquo;. Here, we note the observation of tail bifurcation in the western skink, Plestiodon skiltonianus:
Excitingly, this is the first publication for UNR undergraduate Chasey Danser (pictured below doing field research)- congratulations Chasey!!
(Photo credit: Danielle C. Miles)
[Miles, D.C., Danser, C., and K.T. Shoemaker. 2020. Tail bifurcation in Plestiodon skiltonianus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the conservation status and habitat needs of the pygmy rabbit</title>
      <link>/posts/pygmyrabbit_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/pygmyrabbit_project/</guid>
      <description>The A.P.E. lab is part of a larger team at UNR investigating the population genetics and demography of the pygmy rabbit (Brachylagus idahoensis) in the Great Basin.
To stay up to date on the pygmy rabbit project, led by APE lab PhD student Miranda Crowell, check out her website
UNR collaborators:
 Marjorie Matocq Peter Weisberg and Tom Dilts Jim Sedinger  Other collaborators:
 Sheldon and Hart National Wildlife Refuges, Nevada Department of Wildlife, Great Basin Landscape Conservation Cooperative, Greater Hart-Sheldon Fund  Publications: Crowell, M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the broader ecological impacts of PJ removal</title>
      <link>/posts/pj_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/pj_project/</guid>
      <description>Investigating the broad ecological impacts of Pinyon and Juniper removal in Nevada Thousands of acres of pinyon and juniper woodlands (PJ) will be removed over the next four years to support targeted wildlife populations, notably Greater sage-grouse. We are investigating the effects of PJ removal on insect communities and the bats and reptile species that rely upon them using a rigorous experimental design. Insects can serve as useful indicators of natural disturbances, provide critical pollination services, and represent a major wildlife food resource for many species, including an impressive diversity of bats and reptiles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>