<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Population modeling on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/categories/population-modeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Population modeling on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/categories/population-modeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the broader ecological impacts of PJ removal</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/PJ_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/PJ_project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;investigating-the-broad-ecological-impacts-of-pinyon-and-juniper-removal-in-nevada&#34;&gt;Investigating the broad ecological impacts of Pinyon and Juniper removal in Nevada&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of acres of pinyon and juniper woodlands (PJ) will be removed over the next four years to support targeted wildlife populations, notably Greater sage-grouse. We are investigating the effects of PJ removal on insect communities and the bats and reptile species that rely upon them using a rigorous experimental design. Insects can serve as useful indicators of natural disturbances, provide critical pollination services, and represent a major wildlife food resource for many species, including an impressive diversity of bats and reptiles. Little is known about habitat use and disturbance tolerance for bats and reptiles in the Great Basin. For example, some bat species may benefit from tree removal (e.g., cleared areas may improve foraging or success), while other species may be negatively impacted by tree removal (e.g, loss of roosting sites). We are establishing a set of fixed transects, each spanning a gradient from sagebrush steppe to PJ woodland and monitored 3 to 4 times annually. Transects will be established in four project areas distributed widely across the Great Basin- including the Sheldon-Hart refuges and the Ely region (near Great Basin National Park).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/shoemaker/lab/img/GBLCCschematic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Schematic of study design&#34; /&gt;
At each project area, three transects will be established: one control transect (no tree removal at any point during the four-year study), one pre-treatment transect (tree removal scheduled for year 2 or 3 of the study), and one post-treatment transect (tree removal conducted 1-5 years prior to the initiation of research activities). At regular intervals along each transect, we will monitor the diversity and density of bats, reptiles and insects using an array of active trapping and passive survey methods. Data analysis will focus on evaluating the community-level effects of PJ removal and modeling bat, reptile and insect diversity and abundance as a function of environmental drivers such as vegetation structure, distance from water source, and climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/shoemaker/lab/img/PJ1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Pinyon and Juniper woodland&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling population growth of COTS in Australia&#39;s Great Barrier Reef</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/COTSproject/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/COTSproject/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crown-of-thorns-starfish-project&#34;&gt;Crown-of-Thorns Starfish project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crown-of-Thorns Starfish (C.O.T.S.; &lt;em&gt;Acanthaster planci&lt;/em&gt;) is a native predator of coral. On occasion, C.O.T.S. populations &amp;ldquo;explode&amp;rdquo;, and these outbreaks represent one of the major recognized threats to the Great Barrier Reef in Australia (accounting for 42% of coral loss over the past 30 years). The A.P.E. lab is collaborating with researchers at Australian Institute of Marine Science in Queensland (Sam Matthews and Camille Mellin), James Cook University (Morgan Pratchett) and University of Adelaide (Damien Fordham) to better understand the drivers of C.O.T.S. population explosions and potentially develop strategies for how to reduce this threat to the Great Barrier Reef.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/shoemaker/lab/img/GreatBarrierReefMap.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Map of the Great Barrier Reef&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>