<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Central grasslands ecosystem on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>/categories/central-grasslands-ecosystem/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Central grasslands ecosystem on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/central-grasslands-ecosystem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive modeling of plague die-offs in prairie dog colonies</title>
      <link>/posts/PredictivePlagueDieOff_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/PredictivePlagueDieOff_project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Several published studies have already shown that temperature, precipitation and topography can affect the probability of a die-off event. However, a broader synthesis of datasets from across the BTPD range may enable more accurate prediction of when and where die-offs will occur. The APE lab is leading a large collaborative project to create predictive models of BTPD colony die-offs caused by the plague bacterium.  We have acquired colony history data from across the BTPD range and are working on using machine learning techniques to create a model of plague outbreaks that can help managers determine how best to target their anti-plague management activities (such as &amp;ldquo;dusting&amp;rdquo; for fleas and vaccine administration).  This model will also help us better understand the selection pressures that could lead to &lt;a href=&#34;/posts/PlagueModeling_project/&#34;&gt;genetic resistance to plague&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/PdogBurrow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prairie dog burrow&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A BTPD burrow that has been &amp;ldquo;dusted&amp;rdquo; with insecticide to reduce the probability of plague transmission through fleas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, our team received USDA/NIFA funding to build a more detailed model of boom-bust population dynamics in prairie dog metapopulations as part of a larger project focused on rangeland management:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Understanding how to manage prairie dog population dynamics in the context of plague, climate, and livestock production”. USDA-AFRI. 2020-2023. $496,000 (PI: A.D. Davidson, Colorado State University)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators:&lt;/strong&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;http://anadavidson.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Ana Davidson, Colorado State University&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;http://elizabethhunter.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Elizabeth Hunter, GSU&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fort.usgs.gov/staff-details/512&#34;&gt;David Eads, Colorado State University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the potential for widespread plague resistance in prairie dogs</title>
      <link>/posts/PlagueModeling_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/PlagueModeling_project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Prairie dogs are keystone species of North America’s central grasslands, and have experienced dramatic population reductions over the past century due to sylvatic plague, a highly virulent disease introduced to North America ca. 1900. The APE lab is involved in building a novel host-resistance modeling framework to investigate the genetic, demographic and environmental conditions that promote or impede resistance to plague and other similar virulent pathogens in complex and dynamic ecosystems. The prairie dog-plague system provides an excellent model to understand the conditions under which evolutionary rescue occurs in complex and dynamic ecological systems, and will help illuminate a novel and potential large-scale conservation approach to address 1) the biggest threat facing the prairie dog ecosystem that spans from Canada to Mexico - plague and 2) species around the world threatened with novel diseases and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-novel-modeling-framework-for-understanding-host-resistance-in-complex-real-world-landscapes&#34;&gt;A novel modeling framework for understanding host resistance in complex real-world landscapes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use a flexible lattice population structure in which each node contains a stage-structured host population, allowing integration of spatial raster data of environmental variables and enabling multiple modes of dispersal and disease transmission. Natural selection will be modeled as vital rate reductions contingent upon population-level genetic makeup. Selection pressures will emerge from a statistical epidemiological model of disease incidence and spread. Resistance-conferring, diploid gene loci will be modeled with arbitrary numbers of genes, allelic variants, dominance of resistance, gene interactions (epistasis; we will not model chromosomal linkage) and alternative modes of resistance (i.e., alternative sets of genes/alleles that confer resistance). Coevolution will be modeled as a change in virulence over time. This modeling framework will be written in R/C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Plague Model Schematic1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Schematic of plague model&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-example-videos&#34;&gt;Some example videos&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unstructured landscape&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/45_VITXJgJs&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/45_VITXJgJs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/8PhD-aDqTj4&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/8PhD-aDqTj4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/NaCT5NDUwTo&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/NaCT5NDUwTo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structured landscape&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/fWb79btL8G0&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/fWb79btL8G0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/MFeZLlB0xV8&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/MFeZLlB0xV8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/TF9fVWDkfFA&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/TF9fVWDkfFA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project lead: &lt;a href=&#34;http://anadavidson.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Ana Davidson, CSU&lt;/a&gt;
Modeling lead: &lt;a href=&#34;http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/&#34;&gt;Kevin Shoemaker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key collaborators:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://labs.cas.usf.edu/sackett/Sackett_Lab/People.html&#34;&gt;Loren Cassin Sackett, USF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mggen.nau.edu/&#34;&gt;Joseph Busch, NAU&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nwhc.usgs.gov/staff/katie_richgels.jsp&#34;&gt;Katherine Richgels, USGS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nwhc.usgs.gov/staff/tonie_rocke.jsp&#34;&gt;Tonie Rocke, USGS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://elizabethhunter.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Elizabeth Hunter, GSU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>