<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Elizabeth Hunter</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/Epost20161003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/Epost20161003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a postdoctoral researcher in the A.P.E. lab working on several population modeling projects including: predicting plague outbreaks in black-tailed prairie dogs, using abundance data to predict the effects of competition on songbird responses to climate change, and simulation modeling to inform restoration of giant tortoise populations in the Galapagos Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit my personal webpage &lt;a href=&#34;http://elizabethhunter.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling population growth of COTS in Australia&#39;s Great Barrier Reef</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/COTSproject/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/COTSproject/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crown-of-thorns-starfish-project&#34;&gt;Crown-of-Thorns Starfish project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crown-of-Thorns Starfish (C.O.T.S.; &lt;em&gt;Acanthaster planci&lt;/em&gt;) is a native predator of coral. On occasion, C.O.T.S. populations &amp;ldquo;explode&amp;rdquo;, and these outbreaks represent one of the major recognized threats to the Great Barrier Reef in Australia (accounting for 42% of coral loss over the past 30 years). The A.P.E. lab is collaborating with researchers at Australian Institute of Marine Science in Queensland (Sam Matthews and Camille Mellin), James Cook University (Morgan Pratchett) and University of Adelaide (Damien Fordham) to better understand the drivers of C.O.T.S. population explosions and potentially develop strategies for how to reduce this threat to the Great Barrier Reef.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/shoemaker/lab/img/GreatBarrierReefMap.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Map of the Great Barrier Reef&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A.P.E. Lab at UNR</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/test-post-withimage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/test-post-withimage/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hello-world&#34;&gt;Hello world!!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello world, we are the &lt;em&gt;APE lab&lt;/em&gt;. Follow us on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Kevin Shoemaker</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/shoemaker/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/posts/shoemaker/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kevin-shoemaker&#34;&gt;Kevin Shoemaker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin Shoemaker is the director of the Applied Population Ecology lab at the department of Natural Resources &amp;amp; Environmental Science at the University of Nevada, Reno. Broadly, his research couples ecological data (e.g., census records, mark-recapture data, remote sensing data) with simulation models, statistics and machine learning to support wildlife conservation and management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>