<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>prairie dogs on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>/categories/prairie-dogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in prairie dogs on Applied Population Ecology Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/prairie-dogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive modeling of plague die-offs in prairie dog colonies</title>
      <link>/posts/PredictivePlagueDieOff_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/PredictivePlagueDieOff_project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Several published studies have already shown that temperature, precipitation and topography can affect the probability of a die-off event. However, a broader synthesis of datasets from across the BTPD range may enable more accurate prediction of when and where die-offs will occur. The APE lab is leading a large collaborative project to create predictive models of BTPD colony die-offs caused by the plague bacterium.  We have acquired colony history data from across the BTPD range and are working on using machine learning techniques to create a model of plague outbreaks that can help managers determine how best to target their anti-plague management activities (such as &amp;ldquo;dusting&amp;rdquo; for fleas and vaccine administration).  This model will also help us better understand the selection pressures that could lead to &lt;a href=&#34;/posts/PlagueModeling_project/&#34;&gt;genetic resistance to plague&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/PdogBurrow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prairie dog burrow&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A BTPD burrow that has been &amp;ldquo;dusted&amp;rdquo; with insecticide to reduce the probability of plague transmission through fleas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, our team received USDA/NIFA funding to build a more detailed model of boom-bust population dynamics in prairie dog metapopulations as part of a larger project focused on rangeland management:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Understanding how to manage prairie dog population dynamics in the context of plague, climate, and livestock production”. USDA-AFRI. 2020-2023. $496,000 (PI: A.D. Davidson, Colorado State University)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators:&lt;/strong&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;http://anadavidson.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Ana Davidson, Colorado State University&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;http://elizabethhunter.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;Elizabeth Hunter, GSU&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fort.usgs.gov/staff-details/512&#34;&gt;David Eads, Colorado State University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>