<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Shoemaker Lab at UNR</title>
    <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Shoemaker Lab at UNR</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Kevin T Shoemaker</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Metamodeling for conservation</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/Metamodeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/Metamodeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my postdoctoral postition at Stony Brook University I was lucky to be part of a large NSF-funded collaborative effort (Research Coordination Network, DEB-1146198) that is focused on developing and testing methods to facilitate &amp;ldquo;metamodel&amp;rdquo; linkages among existing ecological modeling platforms. This project was intended to bring multiple independently developed ecological software packages to bear in addressing complex conservation questions via an &amp;ldquo;open data&amp;rdquo; approach (whereby independent software modules can access and modify shared state variables at run-time). I co-led the development of software to facilitate metamodel linkages using the widely-used Ramas Metapop software for population viability analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Australian turtle case study&lt;/strong&gt;: The northern long-necked turtle (&lt;em&gt;Chelodina rugosa&lt;/em&gt;) is a well-studied turtle species that inhabits the savanna ecosystems of northern Australia. Work by Fordham et al. (2008) suggested that the greatest current risk to long-necked turtle populations is posed by feral pig predation. However, the complex interactions between feral pig predation, human harvest, and climate change, may well determine the fate of this species over a longer term. Modeling northern long-necked turtle dynamics requires an ecosystem-level metamodeling approach. This case study is especially interesting because of the strong role of spatial and temporal environmental heterogeneity in driving these interactions. We are investigating dynamic stability operating at multiple scales, regulating the extinction dynamics of the northern long-necked turtle, with a particular focus on how these processes may be altered under climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black-footed ferret case study&lt;/strong&gt;: Strong inter-species interactions (e.g., predator-prey, prey-disease) figure prominently in the risk calculus for the newly reintroduced populations of the black-footed ferret (&lt;em&gt;Mustela nigripes&lt;/em&gt;). To study the dynamics that would result from these interactions, I linked an epidemiological model, a prairie dog metapopulation model, and a ferret population model to investigate ferret extinction risk in plague-affected landscapes. A paper that describes the model and presents findings regarding the spread of plague in prairie dog metapopulations and the consequences for ferret population viability was recently published in the Journal of Applied Ecology. In the next phase of this project, we will extend our models to include a dynamic two-way interaction between ferrets and prairie dogs, and explore the consequences of multi-species interactions in ways that are not possible with a standard single-species modeling approach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using capture-mark-recapture data to improve conservation theory and practice</title>
      <link>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/CMR/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://naes.unr.edu/shoemaker/lab/project/CMR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my dissertation work at SUNY-ESF, I developed a new method for estimating yearling recruitment from mark-recapture data in cases where age information is available (for many turtles, age can be estimated on the basis of annuli &amp;ndash; rings on the scutes of the plastron and/or carapace). More recently, I have been working with colleagues to use a nationwide bird banding database (MAPS: Monitoring Avian Productivity and Survivorship) to parameterize metapopulation models for a broad spectrum of North American avifauna. Also, I am working with colleagues at the University of Rhode Island to use a 100-year mark recapture data set on eastern box turtles (&lt;em&gt;Terrapene c. carolina&lt;/em&gt;) to inform management practices and conservation strategies for this species.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
